I'm Chetan Bhatt
أنا شيتان باهات
and when I give my name, I'm often asked, "Where are you from?"
عندما أخبر أحداً باسمي يتم سؤالي غالباً: "من أين أنت؟"
And I normally say London.
وعادةً أقول من لندن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But of course, I know what they're really asking,
لكن طبعاً، أنا أُدرك ما يسألون عنه حقاً
so I say something like,
لذا أخبرهم بالتالي:
"Well, my grandparents and my mum were born in India,
"حسناً، جداي وأمي وُلدوا في الهند،
my dad and I were born in Kenya,
أنا وأبي ولدنا في كينيا،
and I was brought up in London.
وترعرعت في لندن.
And then they've got me mapped.
وعندها يصنفوني حسب منشأي،
"Ah, you're a Kenyan Asian. I've worked with one of those."
"نعم، أنت كيني آسيوي، لقد سبق وأن عملت مع واحدٍ من هؤلاء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And from my name they probably assume that I'm a Hindu.
وبالنظر إلى اسمي يفترضون أنني هندوسي على الأغلب.
And this sort of fixes me for them.
وذلك يحدد ماهيّتي بالنسبة لهم.
But what about the Christians
ولكن ماذا عن المسيحيين
and the Muslims and the atheists
والمسلمين والملحدين
that I grew up with?
الذين نشأت معهم؟
Or the socialists and the liberals,
أو الاشتراكيين والليبراليين،
even the occasional Tory?
حتى المحافظين في بعض الأحيان؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Indeed, all kinds of women and men --
وبالفعل فإن كل أشكال النساء والرجال،
vegetable sellers, factory workers, cooks, car mechanics --
كبائعي الخضروات وعمال المصانع والطباخين ومكانيكيي السيارات،
living in my working class area,
الذين يعيشون مثلي ضمن هذه الفئة العاملة،
in some profoundly important way,
يعدّون بشكل متأصّل ومهم،
they are also a part of me
جزءاً منّي أيضاً
and are here with me.
وهم هُنا معي.
Maybe that's why I find it hard to respond to questions about identity
ربما ذلك هو السبب أنّني أجد صعوبة في الإجابة على الأسئلة التي تخص الهوية
and about origin.
والأصل.
And it's not just a sort of teenage refusal to be labeled.
وهذا مختلفٌ عن رفض المراهقين لأن يتم تصنيفهم.
It's about our own most identities,
بل هو يتعلّق بشخصياتنا الذاتية،
the ones that we put our hands up to,
تلك التي نؤيدها ونوافقها،
the ones that we cheer for,
والتي نهتف لها،
the ones that we fight for,
والتي نحارب من أجلها،
the ones that we love or hate.
والتي نحبها أو نكرهها.
And it's about how we apprehend ourselves
وهي تتعلق بكيفية إدراكنا لأنفسنا
as well as others.
وللآخرين أيضاً.
And it's about identities we just assume that we have
وهي عن الهويات التي نفترض أننا نملكها
without thinking too much about them.
بدون أن نفكر كثيراً في الأمر.
But our responses to questions of identity and origin
ولكن إجاباتنا في ما يتعلق بالأسئلة عن الهوية والأصل
have substantial social and political importance.
لها أهمية اجتماعية وسياسية جوهرية.
We see the wars, the rages of identity going on all around us.
إذ نرى حولنا الحروب التي تمثل حطام الهوية.
We see violent religious, national and ethnic disputes.
نرى الغضب الديني والنزاعات الوطنيّة والعرقية.
And often the conflict is based on old stories of identity
وغالباً ما تكون أسباب الصراع متعلّقة بقصصٍ قديمةٍ تتعلق بالهوية
and belonging
والانتماء
and origins.
والأصول.
And these identities are based on myths,
وهذه الهويات مبنية على الأساطير،
typically about ancient, primordial origins.
وعادةً تكون عن الأصول القديمة والبدائية.
And these could be about Adam and Eve
وقد تكون هذه الأساطير عن آدم وحواء
or about the supremacy of a caste or gender
أو حول سيادة طائفة أو جنس معيّن
or about the vitality of a supposed race
أو حول رخاء أحد الأعراق بعينه
or about the past glories of an empire or civilization
أو حول الأمجاد التاريخيّة للإمبراطوريات أو الحضارات
or about a piece of land
أو حول الأراضي
that some imagined deity has gifted.
التي وهبتها بعض الآلهة التخيلية.
Now, people say
يعتبر الناس اليوم
that origin stories and identity myths make us feel secure.
أن قصص الأصول وأساطير الهوية تُشعرنا بالأمان.
What's wrong with that?
فما الخطأ في ذلك؟
They give us a sense of belonging.
إنها تُعطينا شعوراً بالانتماء.
Identity is your cultural clothing,
فالهوية هي ملابسك الثقافية،
and it can make you feel warm and fuzzy inside.
وتستطيع أن تجعلك تشعر بالدفء من الداخل.
But does it really?
ولكن هل تفعل ذلك حقاً؟
Do we really need identity myths to feel safe?
هل نحن حقاً بحاجة لأساطير عن الهوية لنشعر بالأمان؟
Because I see religious, national, ethnic disputes
لأنني أرى النزاعات الدينية والوطنية والعرقية
as adding to human misery.
إضافة أُخرى للبؤس الإنساني.
Can I dare you
هل أستطيع تحديك
to refuse every origin myth
في رفض كل أساطير الأصل
that claims you?
التي تشكّلك وتصنعك؟
What if we reject every single primordial origin myth
ماذا لو رفضنا جميع أساطير الأصل البدائية
and develop a deeper sense of personhood,
وقمنا بتنمية إحساس أعمق بالشخصية
one responsible to humanity as a whole
كشخص له واجب تجاه البشرية جمعاء
rather than to a particular tribe,
بدلاً من قبيلة معينة،
a radically different idea of humanity
وهي فكرة مختلفة جذرياً عن الإنسانية
that exposes how origin myths mystify,
والتي تكشف أن أساطير الأصل هي مجرد خرافات
disguise global power,
تخفي خلفها القوة العالمية،
rapacious exploitation,
والاستغلال الجشع،
poverty, the worldwide oppression of women and girls,
والفقر، وقمع النساء والفتيات في أنحاء العالم،
and of course massive, accelerating inequalities?
وطبعاً الزيادة في أوجه عدم المساواة؟
Now, origin myths are closely linked to tradition,
ترتبط خرافات الأصل ارتباطاً وثيقاً بالتقاليد،
and the word tradition points to something old
وكلمة تقاليد تشير إلى شيءٍ قديم
and permanent, almost natural,
ودائم وفطري تقريباً،
and people assume tradition is just history,
ويَفترضُ الناس أن التقاليد هي مجرد تاريخ،
simply the past condensed into a nice story.
ماض ملخص ببساطة في قصة لطيفة.
But let's not confuse tradition with history.
ولكن دعونا لا نخلط بين التقليد والتاريخ.
The two are often in severe conflict.
واللذان في كثير من الأحيان يكونان في صراعٍ شديد.
Origin stories are usually recently created fictions of ancient belonging,
عادة ما تكوّن قصص الأصل خيالاً عن انتماءٍ قديم،
and they're absurd
وهذا أمرٌ سخيفٌ
given the complexity of humanity
نظراً لتعقيد البشرية
and our vastly interconnected, even if very unequal world.
وامتلاكنا لروابط مشتركة، حتى لو كان العالم غير متكافئ جداً.
And today we see claims to tradition
واليوم نرى الادعاءات الخاصة بالتقاليد
that claim to be ancient
التي تدعى أنها قديمة،
changing rapidly in front of our eyes.
تتغير سريعاً أمام أعيننا.
with Asian, English, Caribbean, Irish families living in our street,
كانت تعيش أيضاً عائلات آسيويّة وإنجليزية وكاريبيّة وإيرلندية في شارعنا،
and the neo-Nazi National Front was massive then
وكانت الجبهة الوطنية النازية الجديدة ضخمة وقتها
with regular marches and attacks on us
وكانت تُسيّر المسيرات والهجمات علينا بشكل متكرر
and a permanent threat
كنا تحت تهديدٍ دائم
and often a frequent reality of violence against us
وغالباً ما تتكرر حوادث العنف الحقيقية ضدنا
on the streets, in our homes,
سواءً في الشوارع أو في بيوتنا،
typically by neo-Nazis and other racists.
مُنظّمة عادةً من قبل النازيين الجدد والعنصريين.
And I remember during a general election a leaflet came through our letter box
وأتذكر أنه أثناء الانتخابات العامة أُلقي منشور في صندوق البريد خاصتنا
with a picture of the National Front candidate for our area.
مع صورة لمرشّح الجبهة الوطنية لمنطقتنا.
And the picture
وكانت الصورة
was of our next-door neighbor.
لجارنا الذي يقطن بجوارنا.
He threatened to shoot me once when I played in the garden as a kid,
لقد هددني مرة بالقتل عندما كنت طفلاً ألعب في الحديقة،
and many weekends, shaven-headed National Front activists
وخلال العديد من العطل، كان العديد من الناشطين حليقي الرأس من الجبهة الوطنيّة
and emerged with scores of placards
وأبرزوا العشرات من اللافتات
screaming that they wanted us to go back home.
ينادون بأنهم يريدون أن نعود إلى ديارنا.
But today he's one of my mum's best mates.
ولكنّه اليوم واحدٌ من أفضل أصدقاء أمي.
He's a very lovely, gentle and kind man,
كما أنّه رجل لطيف ومحبوب جداً.
and at some point in his political journey out of fascism
وفي إحدى اللحظات في رحلته السياسية للخروج من الفاشية
he embraced a broader idea of humanity.
اعتنق فكرة الإنسانيّة الواسعة.
There was a Hindu family that we got to know well --
وكانت هناك عائلة هندوسية كنا نعرفها جيداً،
and you have to understand that life in our street
وعليكم أن تفهموا أن الحياة في شارعنا
was a little bit like the setting for an Asian soap opera.
كانت تشبه التحضير لعرض درامي آسيوي.
You really had no choice in this matter.
لم يكن لك أي خيار في هذه المسألة.
But in this family, there was a quiet little boy
ولكن في هذه العائلة، كان هناك صبيٌّ صغيرٌ هادئٌ
who went to the same school as I did,
وقد ذهبنا معًا إلى نفس المدرسة،
and after I left school, I didn't hear much more about him,
وبعد أن تركت المدرسة، لم أعد أسمع الكثير عنه،
except that he'd gone off to India.
باستثناء أنه قد ذهب بعيداً إلى الهند.
Now around 2000,
وحوالي عام 2000،
I remember seeing this short book.
أتذكر رؤية كتابٍ قصير.
The book was unusual
كان الكتاب غير عادي
because it was written by a British supporter of Al Qaeda,
لأنه مكتوب من قبل مؤيدٍ بريطاني لتنظيم القاعدة،
and in it the author calls for attacks in Britain.
ويدعو المؤلف في هذا الكتاب لشن هجمات في بريطانيا.
This is in 1999,
وكان ذلك في عام 1999،
so 9/11 and the invasion of Iraq was still in the future,
ولذلك فإن حادثة 11/9 وغزو العراق كانتا لا تزالان في المستقبل،
and he helped scout New York bombing targets.
وساعد في كشف أماكن التفجير المُستهدفة في نيويورك.
He taught others how to make a dirty bomb to use on the London Underground,
كما علّم الآخرين كيفية صنع عبوة متفجّرة لاستخدامها في مترو أنفاق لندن،
and he plotted a massive bombing campaign in London's shopping areas.
وخطط لحملة تفجير ضخمة في مناطق التسوّق في لندن.
He's a very high-risk security prisoner in the UK
هو الآن سجين في المملكة المتحدة تحت حراسة مشددة
and one of the most important Al Qaeda figures to be arrested in Britain.
وهو واحدٌ من أهم عميلي تنظيم القاعدة الذين اعتُقلوا في بريطانيا.
The author of that book
إن مؤلف هذا الكتاب
was the very same quiet little boy
كان الصبي الصغير نفسه
who went to my school.
الذي ذهب إلى مدرستي.
So a Hindu boy from Britain
إذاً إن هذا الشاب الهندوسي البريطاني
became an Al Qaeda fighter
أصبح عضواً في تنظيم القاعدة
and a most-wanted international terrorist,
وواحداً من أكثر الإرهابيين المطلوبين دولياً،
and he rejected what people would call his Hindu or Indian or British identity,
وتجاهل ما سيدعوه الناس به سواءً هندوسياً أو هندياً أو بريطانياً،
and he became someone else.
وأصبح شخصاً آخر.
He refused to be who he was.
ورفض ما كان عليه.
He recreated himself,
وأعاد تشكيل نفسه،
and this kind of journey is very common
هذا النوع من المسيرات الشخصيّة شائعٌ جداً
for young men and women
للشباب نساءً ورجالاً
who become involved in Al Qaeda or Islamic State
الذين أصبحوا مشاركين في تنظيم القاعدة أو تنظيم الدولة الإسلامية
or other transnational armed groups.
أو الجماعات المسلحة العالميّة الأُخرى.
Al Qaeda's media spokesman is a white American
إن المتحدث الرسمي لتنظيم القاعدة هو شخصٌ أمريكي أبيض
from a Jewish and Catholic mixed background,
من أصل يهودي وكاثوليكي مُختلط،
and neither he nor the boy from my school
ولم يكن هو ولا الصبي الآخر من مدرستي
were from Muslim backgrounds.
من خلفياتٍ مسلمة.
There's no point in asking them where are they from.
ليس هناك أي داعٍ أن نسأل عن أصلهم.
A more important question is where they're going.
السؤال الأهم هو أين هم ذاهبون.
And I would also put it to you
وأود أيضاً أن أوضّح لكم
that exactly the same journey occurs for those young men and women
أن نفس الحادثة بالضبط تحدث لهؤلاء الشبان والشابات
who were brought up in Muslim family backgrounds.
الذين تربوا في عائلات مسلمة.
Most of those who join Al Qaeda
وإن معظم الذين ينضمون إلى القاعدة
and other Salafi jihadi groups from Europe, Asia, North America,
وغيرها من الجماعات الجهادية السلفية من أوروبا وآسيا وأمريكا الشمالية
even in many cases the Middle East
أو حتى وفي كثير من الحالات من الشرق الأوسط
are those who have comprehensively rejected their backgrounds
هم أولئك الذين رفضوا بشكل قاطع خلفياتهم
to become, in essence, new people.
ليصبحوا في أعماقهم أشخاصاً جُدداً.
They spend an enormous amount of time attacking their parents' backgrounds
كما أنهم يقضون قدراً هائلاً من الوقت لمهاجمة أصول والديهم
as profane, impure, blasphemous,
ويعتبرونهم كفاراً أو مدنسين
the wrong type of Islam,
وأنّهم الشكل الخاطئ من الإسلام،
and their vision instead
كما أن رؤيتهم
is a fantastical view of cosmic apocalypse.
هي وجهة نظر خياليّة للنهاية الكونية.
It's a born again vision.
وهي رؤية الولادة من جديد،
Discard your past, your society, your family and friends
عن طريق تجاهل ماضيك ومجتمعك وعائلتك وأصدقائك
since they're all impure.
لأنّهم جميعاً غير طاهرين.
Instead, become someone else,
وأن تكون مختلفًا عنهم،
your true self,
لتجد ذاتك الحقيقية،
your authentic self.
وحقيقتك.
Now, this isn't about a return to the past.
ولا يتعلّق ذلك بالعودة إلى الماضي.
It's about using a forgery of the past
إنّما يتعلق بتزوير الماضي
to envision an appalling future which begins today at year zero.
لكي تستطيع تصوّر مستقبل مروّع يبدأ سنته الأولى من اليوم.
This is why over 80 percent of the victims of Al Qaeda and Islamic State
وهذا السبب في أن أكثر من 80% من ضحايا تنظيم القاعدة والدولة الإسلامية
are people from Muslim backgrounds.
هم أُناسٌ من خلفيات مسلمة.
The first act by Salafi jihadi groups when they take over an area
إن أول ما تفعله الجماعات الجهادية السلفية عندما يستولون على منطقة
is to destroy existing Muslim institutions
هو تدمير المؤسسات الإسلامية الموجودة فيها.
including mosques, shrines, preachers, practices.
بما في ذلك المساجد والأضرحة والدعاة والممارسات.
Their main purpose is to control and punish people internally,
والغرض الرئيسي منها هو السيطرة على المنطقة ومعاقبة الناس فيها،
to dictate the spaces that women may go,
وفرض الأماكن التي يُمكن أن تذهب إليها النساء،
their clothing, family relations,
وفرض ملابسهم وعلاقتهم الأسرية،
beliefs, even the minute detail of how one prays.
ومعتقداتهم وحتى التفاصيل الدقيقة المتعلقة بكيفيّة الصلاة.
And you get the impression in the news
وفي الأخبار يمنحوك انطباعاً
that they are after us in the West,
أنّهم يريدون قتلنا نحن الذين نقطن الغرب،
but they are actually mainly after people from other Muslim backgrounds.
ولكن هم في الواقع يريدون قتل الناس من الخلفيات المسلمة الأخرى بشكل أساسي.
In their view, no other Muslim can ever be pure enough,
وفي اعتقادهم لا يوجد مسلم من خلفيّة أخرى يُمكن أن يكون نقياً بما فيه الكفاية،
so ordinary beliefs and practices that have existed for centuries
ولذلك فإن المعتقدات والممارسات الاعتياديّة التي كانت موجودة لقرون
are attacked as impure
تتم مهاجمتها على أساس أنّها من الكفر
by teenagers from Birmingham or London
من قبل مراهقين من برمنغهام أو لندن
who know nothing
والذين لا يعرفون شيئاً
about the histories that they so joyously obliterate.
عن التاريخ الذي يطمسونه وهم فرحون.
Now here, their claim to tradition is at war with history,
وهنا فإن مطالبتهم بالتقاليد تعتبر كحرب مع التاريخ،
but they're nevertheless very certain about their purity
ولكن مع ذلك، فهم ليسوا متأكدين بشكل قاطع من نقائهم
and about the impurity of others.
ومن عدم طهارة الآخرين.
Purity,
إن النقاء
certainty,
والقناعة
the return to authentic tradition,
والعودة إلى التقاليد الأصيلة
the quest for these can lead to lethal visions
والسعي لتحقيقها يمكن أن يؤدي إلى رؤى قاتلة
of perfect societies and perfected people.
لمجتمعات مثاليّة وأُناس مثاليين.
This is what the main Hindu fundamentalist organization in India
وهذا هو ما تبدو عليه المنظمة الأصوليّة الهندوسيّة في الهند
looks like today at its mass rally.
في تجمّعها الجماهيري اليوم.
Maybe it reminds you of the 1930s in Italy or Germany,
وهذا قد يُذكرك بعقد الثلاثينيات من القرن العشرين في إيطاليا وألمانيا،
and the movement's roots are indeed in fascism.
وجذور هذه الحركة هي بالفعل فاشية.
It was a member of the same Hindu fundamentalist movement
كان أحد أعضاء هذه الحركة الأصولية الهندوسية
who shot dead Mahatma Gandhi.
هو من قتل المهاتما غاندي.
Hindu fundamentalists today view this murderer as a national hero,
والهندوسيين اليوم ينظرون إلى هذا القاتل كبطل وطني،
and they want to put up statues of him throughout India.
ويريدون وضع تماثيل له في جميع أنحاء الهند.
They've been involved for decades
لقد شاركوا على مدى عقود
in large-scale mass violence against minorities.
في أعمال عنف جماعي واسعة النطاق ضد الأقليات.
They ban books, art, films.
كما يحظرون الكتب والفن والأفلام.
They attack romantic couples on Valentine's Day,
ويهاجمون المتحابين في يوم عيد الحب،
Christians on Christmas Day.
والمسيحيين في يوم عيد الميلاد.
They don't like others talking critically
ولا يحبّون الآخرين عندما ينتقدونهم
about what they see as their ancient culture
في ما يعتقدون أنّه ثقافتهم القديمة
or using its images
أو عندما يستخدمون صورهم
or caricaturing it
أو يرسمونها بشكل كاريكتوري
or drawing cartoons about it.
أو بشكل رسوم متحرّكة.
But the people making the strongest possible claims
لكن الناس تقدّم أقوى الادعاءات الممكنة
about ancient, timeless Hindu religion
عن الديانة الهندوسية القديمة والخالدة
are dressed in brown shorts and white shirts
ويرتدون السراويل البنية والقمصان البيضاء
while claiming, oddly,
بينما يدّعون بشكل غريب،
to be the original Aryan race,
أنّهم هم العرق الآري الأصلي،
just like the violent Salafi jihadis
تماماً مثل الجهاديين السلفيين العنيفين
who make their claims about their primordial religion
الذين يدّعون تطبيقهم للدين الأصلي.
while dressed in black military uniforms
وهم يرتدون الزي العسكري الأسود
and wearing balaclavas.
ويرتدون أقنعة.
These people are manufacturing pure, pristine identities of conviction
هؤلاء الناس يتصنعون النقي والإيمان الراسخ القوي
and of certainty.
واليقين.
Fundamentalists see religion and culture as their sole property, a property.
يرى الأصوليون الدين والثقافة كممتلكاتهم الخاصة، وأنّهم يملكونها.
But religions and cultures are processes.
ولكن الأديان والثقافات هي عمليات.
They're not things. They're impermanent. They're messy. They're impure.
وهي ليست أشياءً دائمة، بل هي فوضوية وهي غير نقيّة.
Look at any religion and you'll see disputes and arguments
انظر إلى أي دين وسترى النزاعات والخلافات
going all the way down.
موجودة في كل مكان.
Any criticism of religion in any form
إن أي انتقاد للدين بأي شكل من الأشكال
has to therefore be
يجب أن يكون لهذا السبب
part of the expansive sense of humanity
جزءاً من الإحساس الواسع بالإنسانية
we should aspire to.
التي يجب أن نطمح إليها.
I respect your right to have and to express your religion
أنا أحترم حقك في أن يكون لك دينك وأن تعبر عنه،
or your culture or your opinion,
أو ثقافتك أو رأيك،
but I don't necessarily have to respect the content.
ولكن ليس بالضرورة أن أحترام محتواه.
I might like some of it.
قد يعجبني بعضه.
I might like how an old church looks, for example,
قد يروقني منظر الكنيسة القديمة على سبيل المثال،
but this isn't the same thing.
ولكن هذا مختلف عن ذاك.
Similarly, I have a human right
وبالمثل، فإن لدي حق إنساني
to say something that you may find offensive,
في أن أقول شيئاً قد تجده أنت مهيناً،
but you do not have a human right not to be offended.
ولكن ليس لديك حق إنساني في عدم التعرض للإهانة.
In a genuine democracy, we're constantly offended
وفي جوٍّ من الديمقراطية الحقيقية فإننا عرضة للإهانة باستمرار
since people express different views all the time.
بما أن الناس يبدون وجهات نظر مختلفة دوماً.
They also change their views,
كما يغيرون وجهات نظرهم،
so their views are impermanent.
وبالتالي فإن آرائهم غير دائمة.
You cannot fix someone's political views
كما لا يمكنك إصلاح وجهات النظر السياسيّة لشخص ما
based on their religious or national or cultural background.
على أساس دينهم أو خلفيتهم الوطنية أو الثقافية.
Now, these points about religious purity
وهذه النقاط التي تدور حول النقاء الديني
also apply to nationalism and to racism.
تنطبق أيضاً على القومية والعنصرية.
I'm always puzzled
وأشعر دوماً بالتعجب
to have pride in your national or ethnic identity,
عند الافتخار بالجنسيّة أو العرقيّة،
pride in the accident of birth from a warm and cozy womb,
والفخر بولادة طفل من رحم دافء ومريح،
belief in your superiority because of the accident of birth.
وأن تعتقد أنّك متفوّق عن الآخرين بحادثة الولادة.
These people have very firm ideas
هؤلاء الناس لديهم أفكار ثابتة جداً
about what belongs and what doesn't belong
حول ما ينتمي وما لا ينتمي
inside the cozy national cultures that they imagine.
إلى الثقافات الوطنية المريحة التي يتصورونها.
And I'm going to caricature a bit here, but only a little bit.
وسأقوم بتشبيه كاريكاتيري هنا بعض الشيء.
I want you to imagine the supporter of some Little Englander
أريدكم أن تتخيلوا شخصاً معارضاً لسياسة إنكلترا ودورها
or British nationalist political party,
أو للحزب السياسي القومي البريطاني،
and he's sitting at home
وهو جالسٌ في منزله
and he's screaming about foreigners
يصرخ وينادي ضد الأجانب
invading his country
الذين يغزون ويملؤون بلده
while watching Fox News,
وهو يشاهد قناة فوكس نيوز،
an American cable channel
وهي قناة تلفزيونيّة أمريكية،
owned by an Australian
يملكها شخص أسترالي،
on his South Korean television set
على جهاز تلفاز مصنوع في كوريا الجنوبيّة،
which was bought by his Spanish credit card
والذي اشتراه بواسطة بطاقته الائتمانيّة الإسبانيّة،
which is paid off monthly by his high-street British bank
والتي يتم دفعها شهرياً بواسطة بنكه البريطاني رفيع المستوى،
which has its headquarters in Hong Kong.
والذي يقع مقرّه في هونغ كونغ.
He supports a British football team owned by a Russian.
وهذا الشخص يدعم فريق كرة قدم بريطاني يملكه روسي.
His favorite brand of fish and chips
وصنفه المفضل من السمك ورقائق البطاطس
is owned by a Swedish venture capitalist firm.
تملكه شركة رأسماليّة سويديّة.
The church he sometimes goes to
والكنيسة التي يذهب إليها أحياناً
has its creed decided in meetings in Ghana.
تعقد اجتماعات العقيدة في غانا.
His Union Jack underpants
وسراويله الداخلية من شركة يونين جاك
were made in India.
صُنعت في الهند.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And --
وأيضاً...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
And they're laundered regularly
وتغسلها باستمرار
by a very nice Polish lady.
سيدة بولندية لطيفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There is no pure ethnicity, national culture,
لا يوجد هناك أي عرق أو ثقافة وطنيّة نقيّة
and the ethical choices we have today
والخيارات الأخلاقية التي نملكها اليوم
are far wider than being forced to choose
هي أوسع بكثير من الإجبار على الاختيار
between racist right and religious right visions,
بين رؤى الحق العنصري والحق الديني،
dismal visions of culture.
والرؤى الكئيبة للثقافة.
Now, culture isn't just about language, food, clothing and music,
إن الثقافة ليست فقط عبارة عن لغة وطعام وملابس وموسيقى،
but gender relations, ancient monuments,
لكنّها عبارة عن العلاقة بين الجنسين، والمعالم القديمة،
a heritage of sacred texts.
والنصوص المقدسة الموروثة.
But culture can also be what has been decided to be culture
ولكن الثقافة أيضاً هي ما يمكن أن يتم تحديده ليكون ثقافة
by those who have a political stake
بواسطة أولئك الذين يملكون مصالح سياسية
in pounding culture into the shape of a prison.
في تشكيل الثقافة كشكل السجن.
Big political identity claims are elite bids for power.
إن المطالب الكبرى بالهوية السياسية ما هي إلا نداء نخبوي للسلطة.
They're not answers to social or economic or political injustices.
وهذه ليست إجابات على الظلم الاجتماعي أو الاقتصادي أو السياسي.
They often obscure them.
وغالباً ما تحجب هذه الإجابات.
And what about the large number of people across the globe
وماذا عن العدد الكبير من الناس حول العالم
who can't point to a monument from their past,
الذين لا يمكن أن يشيروا إلى نصب تذكاري من ماضيهم،
who don't possess a sacred written text,
الذين لا يمتلكون نصاً مقدساً مكتوباً،
who can't hark back
الذين لا يستطيعون العودة
to the past glories of a civilization or empire?
إلى الأمجاد السابقة لحضارة أو إمبراطورية؟
Are these people less a part of humanity?
هل هؤلاء الناس أقل إنسانيّةً؟
What about you,
ماذا عنك،
now, listening to this?
الآن، أنت الذي تستمع إلى هذا؟
What about you and your identity,
ماذا عن عنك وعن هويتك؟
because you stitch your experiences and your thoughts into a continuous person
لأنك تضع خبراتك وأفكارك داخل شخص معيّن يستمر
moving forward in time.
بالتقدّم في الوقت.
And this is what you are when you say,
وهذا هو ما أنت عليه عندما تقول،
"I," "am," or "me."
"أنا" أو "لي".
But this also includes all of your hopes and dreams,
و لكن هذا يتضمن أيضاً كل آمالك وأحلامك،
all of the you's that could have been,
كل ما يمكن أن تكونه،
and it includes all the other people
ويتضمن كل الأشخاص الآخرين
and the things that are in the biography of who you are.
والأشياء الموجودة في سيرة حياة شخصيتك.
They, the others,
هم -أي الآخرون-
are also a part of you,
يعتبرون جزءاً منك أيضاً،
moving forward with you.
ويتقدمون للأمام معك.
Your authentic self, if such a thing exists,
إن نفسك الأصيلة -إن وُجد شيء من هذا القبيل-
is a complex, messy and uncertain self,
هي معقدة وفوضويّة وغير مُثبتة بحد ذاتها،
and that is a very good thing.
وهذا شيء جيد جداً.
Why not value those impurities and uncertainties?
لماذا لا نقدر تلك الشكوك وعدم اليقين؟
Maybe clinging to pure identities is a sign of immaturity,
ربما يُعد التمسك بالهويات النقيّة علامةً على عدم النضج
and ethnic, nationalist and religious traditions are bad for you.
والعرقيّة والقومية والتقاليد الدينية هي أمور سيئة بالنسبة لك.
Why not be skeptical about every primordial origin claim
لماذا لا تكون كثير الشك في كل أصل بدائي
made on your behalf?
مُقدم دون أخذ رأيك؟
Why not reject the identity myths that call on you to belong,
لماذا لا ترفض أساطير الهوية التي تطلب منك أن تنتمي،
that politicians and community leaders,
والتي يَسِمك بها السياسون وقادة المجتمع،
so-called community leaders,
أو أشباه قادة المجتمع؟
If we don't need origin stories and fixed identities,
إذا لم نكن بحاجة إلى قصص الأصل والهوية الثابتة
we can challenge ourselves to think creatively
فإنّنا نستطيع أن نتحدى أنفسنا بالتفكير الخلّاق
about each other and our future.
عن الآخرين وعن مستقبلنا.
And here culture always takes care of itself.
وهنا فالثقافة تستطيع دوماً أن تتعني بنفسها.
I'm not worried about culture.
أنا لست قلقاً على الثقافة.
Cultures are creative, dynamic processes,
فالثقافات هي عمليات ديناميكية وخلّاقة.
not imposed laws and boundaries.
وليست قوانين وقيودًا مفروضة.
This is Abu al-Walid Muhammad ibn Ahmad ibn Rushd,
هذا هو أبو الوليد محمد بن أحمد بن رشد،
a very senior Muslim judge and thinker in Cordoba in the 12th century,
قاضٍ مسلم مرموق جداً ومفكر في قرطبة في القرن 12،
and his writings were considered deeply blasphemous, heretical and evil.
اعتُبرت كتاباته تكفيريةً وهرطقةً وشراً.
Long after he died,
ولفترة طويلة بعد وفاته،
followers of his work were ruthlessly hunted down,
تم الحكم على متابعيه،
banished and killed over several centuries
بالنفي أو بالقتل وذلك على مدى عدة قرون
by the most powerful religious institution of the medieval period.
من قبل أقوى المؤسسات الدينية في العصور الوسطى.
That institution was the Roman Catholic Church.
تلك المؤسسة هي الكنيسة الكاثوليكية الرومانية.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because ibn Rushd said that something true in religion
لأن ابن رشد قال أن شيئاً حقيقياً في الدين
may conflict with something
قد يتعارض مع شيء
that your reason finds to be true on earth,
يجده منطقك صحيحاً على أرض الواقع،
but the latter is still true.
و لكن هذا الأخير لا يزال صحيحاً.
There are two distinct worlds of truth,
هناك عالَمان مختلفان للحقيقة،
one based on our reason and evidence, and one that is divine,
واحد يستند إلى منطقنا وأدلتنا وواحد إلهي،
and the state, political power, social law are in the realm of reason.
وتندرج الدولة والسلطة السياسية والقانون الاجتماعي في عالم المنطق.
Religious life is a different realm.
في حين أن الحياة الدينية عالم مختلف.
They should be kept separated.
يجب أن يبقيا منفصلين.
Social and political life should be governed by our reason,
فالحياة السياسية والاجتماعية يجب أن تدار بمنطقنا،
not by religion.
وليس بالدين.
And you can see why the church was upset by his writings,
وتستطيعون أن تروا لماذا كانت الكنيسة منزعجة من كتاباته،
as indeed were some Muslims during his lifetime,
كما كان واقع بعض المسلمين خلال فترة حياته،
because he gives us a strong statement of secularism
لأنه أعطانا بياناً قوياً عن العلمانية
of a kind which is normal in Europe today.
في أبهى تجلياتها في أوروبا الآن.
Now, history plays many tricks on us.
والتاريخ الآن يمارس علينا بعض الخدع.
It undermines our fixed truths
فهو يُضعف بعض الحقائق الثابتة لدينا
and what we believe to be our culture and their culture.
وما نؤمن به ليكوّن ثقافتنا وثقافتهم.
Ibn Rushd, someone who happens to be a Muslim,
كان ابن رشد شخصًا مسلماً،
is considered one of the key influences
وهو يعتبر من التأثيرات الأساسية
in the introduction and spread of secularism in Europe.
في تقديم وانتشار العلمانية في أوروبا.
So against religious, nationalist and racial purists of all kinds,
إذاً ضد التطرف الديني والوطني والعنصرية من كل الأنواع،
can you make his story a part of your own,
هل تستطيع أن تجعل قصته جزءاً منك،
not because he happened to be a Muslim,
ليس لأنه كان مسلماً،
not because he happened to be an Arab,
وليس لأنه كان عربياً،
but because he was a human being
بل لأنّه كان إنساناً
with some very good ideas
يملك بعض الأفكار الجيدة
that shook his world
التي هزت عالمه
and ours.
وعالمنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)